Rabbotai רבותי, Rabbotai, we are starting today דף קי"ג Daf Kuf Yud
Gimmel and this thing isn't working.
We're starting today דף קי"ג Daf Kuf Yud Gimmel
and where do we pick up? I believe very top of the
עמוד. amud. Yes, okay, the very first word: ולימא ליה. uleimalay. So,
we had discussed that if you salted your fish and
your meat together, we were concerned that
the blood from the meat went into the fish. And then we
actually had a case about when you salt כשר kosher meat and
it turned out to be טריפה treif meat together, that although the
blood is not a problem, we're concerned about the juices that run
off from the טריפה treif meat. So again the principle is that
when you salt כשר kosher meat, the blood runs off and it's
somehow slippery, דם מטרח סריך, dam mitrach sarich, and doesn't get absorbed
into other כשר kosher pieces of meat that you are salting. But
if you are salting things that are not meat, like fish, then
that's more absorbent, or non-כשר kosher meat, then that's also a problem
because then
forget the blood, but the juices will be absorbed. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara continues on
קי"ג עמוד א'. Kuf Yud Gimmel Amud Alef. ולימא ליה מדישמואל, uleimalay
midei Shmuel, when you're trying to prove that salting pieces of כשר
kosher and not כשר kosher together is a problem and you quoted
the teachings that juices were forbidden of not כשר kosher meat, why
didn't you try to prove it from שמואל's Shmuel statement? דאמר שמואל
de'amar Shmuel because שמואל Shmuel says מליח הרי הוא כרותח maliach harei
hu kerose'ach that salted is like it is boiled, וכבוש הרי הוא
כמבושל ve'kavush harei hu kemevushal and pickled is like it's cooked together.
So if salted is like it's being roasted together, presumably he was
talking exactly about just such a scenario of salting כשר kosher and
not כשר kosher meat together that it caused transfer. So why couldn't
you infer it from שמואל? Shmuel? And the answer is obvious because
that is not clear what things you're salting together and it doesn't
prove that juices of not כשר kosher meat are not כשר. kosher.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אי משמואל ee mi-Shmuel if it's just
from שמואל Shmuel הוה אמינא hava amina I would have
thought הני מילי דמן hani mili daman that's talking about blood. That's
talking, for example, if you had the blood which was together with
fish like our example the other day, or the blood got absorbed
into for all I know vegetables,
or you salted meat in a vessel that didn't have a hole
so the meat sat in its own blood. So yes, it told
me the principle that salting transfers, but it did not tell me
that the juices of not כשר kosher meat are equally טריפה. treif.
אבל צירן ורוטבן aval tziran verotvan
but the brine and the juices לא, lo, I would not have
known that that's considered טריפה. treif. קמ"ל kama shemlan that it is.
So there's two principles. One is what causes the transfer: being salted
causes transfer, מליח כרותח. maliach kerose'ach. And the other is what things
are forbidden. Now we know blood is forbidden, we know non-כשר kosher
things are forbidden. What about the gravy, the juices that come from
non-כשר kosher meat? So that's why we had to quote the verse
that we did yesterday הטמאים hatme'im לאסור צירן ורוטבן. l'esor tziran verotvan.
You combine it together, you know the juices are not כשר, kosher,
you know that salt causes transfer, it's not a special case of
blood which just slides off. So that's how we can learn that
in that case the כשר kosher and not כשר kosher meat salted
together becomes non-כשר. kosher. Yes.
Implicit in that is let's say you could have inferred from שמואל,
Shmuel, you'd prefer שמואל Shmuel to a מדרש הלכה, midrash halacha, why
would you do
that if this is הטמאים hatme'im which is דאורייתא?
de'oraisa? It's a good question. Take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, the
first line. אף על גב דברייתא עדיפא. af al gav de'braisa adifa.
So he says yes the ברייתא braisa tells you, but each part,
שמואל Shmuel and the ברייתא, braisa, each have part of the equation.
The ברייתא braisa tells you the juices are forbidden but they don't
tell me that salted is a way of transferring taste. So the
גמרא Gemara is basically saying why emphasize the ברייתא, braisa, why not
first teach me the idea that salted stuff transfers taste? And the
גמרא's Gemara basic answer: each one is half of the puzzle. שמואל
Shmuel tells you the salted transfers taste and the ברייתא braisa tells
you that the juices are a problem. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says מיתיבי, meisvei,
I'll ask you on this. Now what we're going to be talking
about here is now we're going to focus on the mechanics of
מליח. maliach. We spoke before about how salted it has to be,
מליח הרי הוא כרותח, maliach harei hu kerose'ach, it has to be
that salted is like it's heated up. How salted? אינו נאכל מחמת
מלחו, eino ne'echal machmat milcho, it can't be eaten. We discussed the
debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot whether that means heavily heavily
salted like for preserving or just the salting that you do for
getting the blood, for doing מליחה melichah to get out the blood,
which is certainly what the גמרא Gemara sounds like. So that's a
degree of how much salted. Actually I should just take parenthetically for
those that want to learn all the הלכות halakhot of מליחה, melichah,
that part of תוספות's Tosafot discussion about how come after you salt
meat and it sits around and the blood is on the surface,
why doesn't that blood get reabsorbed by the salt because now it's
salty, the blood that's on the surface of the meat that came
out? And one of תוספות's Tosafot answers is that maybe the salt
after it gets the blood out stops working.
Very convenient. So it works enough to get the blood out and
then it stops working so it doesn't put the blood back in.
So anyway, that's like how, that's the question of how much salt,
when does it start working, how long do you have to leave
it salted, you know, as long as it takes for something, you
know, תוספות Tosafos says it works as long as it's sort of
drawing out the blood. Anyway, that's one question. The next questions are
which things have to be salted? Because if you talk about normal
transfer of taste, it doesn't matter which object is hot. If you
have hot chicken falling into cold milk or or cold chicken falling
into hot milk, either way the taste is transferred. There is a
question that the גמרא Gemara discusses in פסחים, Pesachim, which is if
one is hot and one is cold, maybe and we know like
if something hot falls into something cold eventually it all cools off,
right? So maybe it matters not whether the טריפה treif object is
hot or cold, but whether the bottom one is hot or cold.
The גמרא Gemara thinks that if the bottom one is hot, that
heats things up more than if the top one is hot and
the bottom is cold, which actually makes sense in terms of science
because heat rises, so if the bottom is hot it will heat
things up more than if the top one is hot. But again,
it doesn't matter which is טריפה, treif, which is כשר. kosher. If
you have hot חזיר chazir falling into cold soup or or a
cold piece of chicken falling into hot חזיר chazir soup, I'm sorry,
the opposite, or cold חזיר chazir falling into hot soup, right, the
question is not whether the כשר kosher one is טריפה treif or
or כשר, kosher, whether the כשר kosher one is hot or cold,
the question is at most whether it's the top or the bottom
one that's hot or cold. That's when it comes to heat. When
it comes to saltiness, we're about to see now that there's a
difference. Because what would happen if I salted a כשר kosher chicken,
let's even forget about blood, I salted fish, כשר kosher fish, together
with not כשר kosher fish that weren't salted and I put them
on top of one another. What would happen? So should that be
a problem? So that means if you think that salt is like
heat, yes it should be a problem. But if you think about
how salt really works, what is the salt going to do on
the כשר kosher fish? It draws out the juices. So I have
salted כשר kosher fish and not salted טריפה treif fish and I
put them on top of one another. Is the טריפה treif fish
going to come into the כשר kosher fish, the juices? No. The
salt will only draw out the taste of the כשר kosher fish.
So different than heat, when it comes to salt, what matters is,
it only matters, the key is if one of them is salted
and the one that is key to be salted is the not
כשר. kosher. Only if the not כשר kosher one is salted does
it matter. Okay, you get that? When it comes to heat, then
you put them together, heat causes transfer, heat will transfer from one
object to the other. I don't care which object, whether it's the
כשר kosher or the טריפה treif that's hot. At most what I
care is if it's the top or the bottom because heat rises.
But I don't care כשר kosher or not כשר. kosher. When it
comes to salted, because the primary way salt works is to draw
out the juices, then the only thing that's going to matter by
salted is if the טריפה treif one is salted. If the כשר
kosher is salted and the טריפה treif is not, it won't matter.
I'll take your question in a minute, let's read it in the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: מיתיבי, Meisivei,
ask you on שמואל's Shmuel teaching, on this teaching about if you
salt two טריפה, treif, two things together they transfer taste.
Here's what the ברייתא Braisa says: דג טהור שמלחו עם דג טמא,
Dag tahor shemalcho im dag tamei,
you salted a כשר kosher fish with a non-כשר kosher fish, okay,
cod with octopus, מותר, mutar,
it's permissible. Okay, now here it's that you salted both of them,
which is exactly our scenario, and we're assuming that the same principle
that applies when you salt multiple pieces of meat together, if they're
too busy spewing out their juices they can't absorb other juices, applies
here as well. If they're both salted, so even the כשר kosher
one is busy spewing out its juices, it can't absorb from the
non-כשר. kosher. So you see you're wrong what you said before. Before
you said if you salted both of them it's a problem, here
we say if they're both salted that saves them because the כשר
kosher one is too busy with spewing out its own juices. דג
טהור שמלחו עם דג טמא מותר. Dag tahor shemalcho im dag tamei
mutar. מאי לאו דשניהם מלוחים, Mai lav deshneihem meluchim, are we not
talking that they were both salted? And that's a proof against what
we said yesterday. לא, כגון שהיה טהור מליח וטמא תפל. Lo, kegon
shehaya tahor maliach vetamei tafel.
The כשר kosher one was salted and the non-כשר, kosher, טמא tamei
was תפל. tafel. תפל Tafel means like plain or whatever, unspiced, not
salted. Okay, it's the opposite of מליח. maliach. So when we say
that it's not a problem, it's if the כשר kosher one was
salted and the טריפה treif one was not salted. Because since the
way salt works is to draw juices, if the טריפה treif one
is unsalted, you're totally safe. That's the case where it's okay. But
if they're both salted it is a problem. So the גמרא Gemara
says והא מדקתני סיפא, Veha midekatni seifa, but the end says, if
you look at the side it switches the גירסא, girsa, היה טהור
מליח וטמא תפל מותר, Haya tahor maliach vetamei tafel mutar,
if the כשר kosher one was salted and the non-כשר kosher one
was unsalted, the octopus was unsalted, it's מותר. mutar. מכלל דרישא, Michlal
dereisha, it follows that the first case, בשניהם מלוחים עסקינן, bishneihem meluchim
askinan, is talking that they're both salted and saying even if they're
both salted it's כשר kosher because the spewing out of the juices
prevents it from absorbing juices. So the גמרא Gemara says לא, פירושי
קמפרש, Lo, perushei kamfaresh,
the second case is explaining the first case. It says two both
of them are salted? I says if you salted them, what does
it? טהור שמלחו עם דג טמא מותר. tahor shemelacho im dag tamei
mutar.
If you salted them together it's מותר mutar under what cases is
it מותר? mutar? If you salted your cod with your octopus. כיצד?
keitzad? שהיה טהור מליח וטמא תפל. shehaya tahor maliach vetamei tafel.
Only in the case where the kosher one was salted and the
octopus was not salted.
So the גמרא Gemara says so that's what, that's the case where
it's allowed, when the טרף treif one was unsalted. But if they're
both salted, it will be a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says
הכא נמי מסתברא, hacha nami mistavra, that makes sense that that's how
you should read it. דאי סלקא דעתך רישא שנים מלוחים, de'i salka
daitach reisha shnayim meluchim, if the first case said if they're both
salted it's כשר. kosher. השתא שנים מלוחים שרי, hashta shnayim meluchim sharei,
if they're both salted if even the octopus is salted, but if
they're both salted it's כשר, kosher, טהור מליח וטמא תפל מיבעיא? tahor
maliach vetamei tafel mibaya?
You don't need to tell me that if only the kosher one
was salted. If you've already told me if they're both salted it's
כשר, kosher, then certainly it's כשר kosher if only the kosher one
was salted. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אם משום הא לא
איריא, im mishum ha lo irya, if that was your only point
it would not be a proof. תנא סיפא לגלויי רישא. tana seifa
legiluyei reisha. We taught the first case to reveal what we're talking
about in the second case... excuse me, we taught the second case
to reveal what we're talking about in the first case. דלא תימא
רישא טהור מליח וטמא תפל אבל שנים מלוחים אסור. delo teima reisha
tahor maliach vetamei tafel aval shnayim meluchim assur. You should not think
that I could say the first case actually is saying that if
they're both salted it's כשר. kosher. So if you've already... like again,
what's the case? The ברייתא Braita says like this: If you salted
kosher and not kosher fish, מותר. mutar. If you salted just the
kosher one, מותר. mutar. So we want to know what's the first
case when it says if you salted kosher and not kosher together.
It sounds like it means they're both salted and you see even
if they're both salted it's okay. Says no, maybe it's saying if
you salted them it's מותר mutar in what scenario? When you just
salted the kosher fish. So the גמרא Gemara is saying is, well
you know what that actually makes sense, because if the first case
meant if they're both salted it's כשר, kosher, why do you have
to tell me if just the kosher one is salted? Obviously that's
less problematic. So the גמרא Gemara says no, no, no, that doesn't...
that's not a proof. Maybe we mean both salted is כשר. kosher.
But the reason then we're saying if the kosher one is salted
it's כשר kosher is so that it's clear that the first case
is talking about both of them. Because if I had not said
the case of just the kosher one, you would have said that
was the first case. Now that I said just the case of
the kosher one, you understand that the first case means both of
them salted. So you can't prove from the ברייתא Braita whether we're
talking about two cases or one case. Okay, so... רישא דטהור מליח
וטמא תפל אבל שנים מלוחים אסור.
reisha detahor maliach vetamei
tafel aval shnayim meluchim assur.
I would have thought that... that... that if they're both salted it's
forbidden. תנא סיפא טהור מליח וטמא תפל. tana seifa tahor maliach vetamei
tafel. So the second case says that if the kosher one is
salted it's
כשר. kosher. מכלל דרישא שנים מלוחים, miklal d'reisha shnayim meluchim, is even
both salted ואפילו הכי שרי, ve'afilu hachi sharei,
and nevertheless it's permitted. So what do we say? We have the
ברייתא Braita that says the simple case is just the kosher one
is salted is כשר. kosher. Why? For the reason I told you,
because then only the juices of the kosher one come out, the
unkosher one is... is... you know, no impact if the טרף treif
one is not salted. What if they're both salted? So then the
טרף treif juices are coming out. So is that a problem? Maybe
because the kosher one is spewing out its own juices it protects
it. Okay, so that's the question of what is the ברייתא Braita
saying. In the simple sense, the ברייתא Braita is saying the simple
read that if they're both salted it's כשר, kosher, which goes against
what we said yesterday. Yesterday we said if you salt them both,
the טרף treif juices will come into the kosher. So the גמרא
Gemara says you can't prove it from the ברייתא. Braita. The ברייתא
Braita might mean that if they're both salted it's כשר, kosher, but
it might also mean if you salt them it's כשר kosher under
what scenario? If you just salt the kosher one. But if you
salt them both, then אין הכי נמי in hachi nami it would
be not כשר. kosher. Let's just finish this and then I'll take
your question, because now we're going to look at the end of
the ברייתא. Braita. תא שמע מסיפא דסיפא. ta shema miseifa d'seifa. Come
and hear from the very end. What does the very end say?
אבל אם היה טמא מליח וטהור תפל אסור. aval im haya tamei
maliach vetahor tafel assur. If the... if the octopus were salted and
the cod was not salted, then it's forbidden. טמא מליח וטהור תפל
הוא דאסור. tamei maliach vetahor tafel hu d'assur. It sounds like that's
the only case it's forbidden. When the טרף treif one was salted
and the kosher one was not salted. הא שנים מלוחים. ha shnayim
meluchim. It implies that if they were both salted שרי, sharei, it
sounds like it would be permitted. So it sounds like the only
טרף treif case is when just the טרף treif one is salted.
So גמרא Gemara says no, that doesn't prove it. איידי דתנא רישא
טהור מלוח וטמא תפל, aidi detana reisha tahor maluach vetamei tafel, since
the first case said that if the kosher one was salted it's
כשר, kosher, תנא נמי סיפא טמא מליח וטהור תפל. tana nami seifa
tamei maliach vetahor tafel. The second case says if the טרף treif
one was salted it's טרף. treif. But you cannot prove from the
ברייתא Braita what is the story if both are salted. Now the
גמרא Gemara is, you know, the סתם דגמרא stam d'Gemara is right,
of course, that the simple read of the ברייתא Braita is unquestionably
that if both of them are salted it's כשר. kosher. Here's what
the whole ברייתא Braita says: If you salt kosher and not kosher
fish together, כשר. kosher. If you salt just the kosher fish, כשר.
kosher. If you salt the not kosher fish, טרף. treif. So it
sounds pretty clear that if you salted them both, that was the
first scenario and it's כשר. kosher. But the גמרא Gemara says you
can't absolutely prove it. Maybe
the first was an opening heading. If you salt kosher fish
and not
kosher fish... It doesn't sound that way, but the גמרא Gemara says
it's possible to read the ברייתא Baraita that way, you can't prove
it. So the upshot is what? That we don't feel the ברייתא
Baraita is an absolute proof against us, and we end with the
principle that if you salt two pieces of meat together, if you
salt two pieces of meat together and they're getting out the blood,
then you're okay. That's a special principle about salting to get out
blood, that the blood from one piece does not get absorbed into
the other. However, if they are of different types, fish and meat,
or same types but not blood, two meat and not כשר kosher
meat, so we're also dealing with juices, then we say even though
the כשר kosher one is spewing out its own juices, it can
absorb the טרף. treif.
Why is that?
So both, why not? I mean, why do we have to say...
you get out the blood it's not absorbed, and why if it's
getting out...
Because basically, here's the basic story. You see this huge תוספות? Tosafot?
Basically, we know that salting meat works. So we have to say,
we basically we work backwards. We know that salting meat works, even
multiple pieces of blood together, so we basically have to assume whatever
special principles are operative are operative in that case, and they work
for the salting of the meat, but we don't apply them to
other cases. Now you're right, it would have been nice if at
least in some other areas we would have seen the same application.
So it would have been nice if at least this idea while
you're spewing you don't absorb would have applied, but we don't. That's
exactly what the גמרא Gemara is dealing with, and in the end,
whatever special principles we need by blood we apply to blood, everything
else doesn't go by it, so even if they're both salted it
can absorb. But again, the way in which salting is different than
heat is that by heat it doesn't matter whether the כשר kosher
or the טרף treif is hot, you put them together they get
each other hot, at most what matters is which is on the
top, which is on the bottom. The bottom matters more because heat
rises, whereas by salt it's only a problem if the טרף treif
one is salted, because then it would... juices will come out and
and get into the כשר kosher one. If it's just the כשר
kosher one, it is not a problem. You had a question?
Yeah, you were mentioning that it has when there's a couple ways
of explaining אינו נאכל מחמת מלחו, eino ne'echal machmat milcho, right? Right.
But you know, but let's say you put a whole bunch of
table salt, not כשר kosher salt, it's thicker, isn't it? More flavorful?
Yeah. But you even put a whole bunch of table salt, I
wouldn't want to eat it, like this mound of table salt. Could
be. Yeah. Oh, so it would apply to that too?
Yeah, could very well apply to that too. Okay. Now the reason
that we use כשר kosher salt by the way for הכשר kashering
is because it well I think because it like sort of sits
more near the... first of all, the reason כשר kosher salt is
a better use is better salt in general when you're salting your
meat or when you're salting your food is because you use less
amount of salt and it covers more surface. So like because the
כשר kosher salt pieces are flatter and bigger, they're larger, so to
get a piece of meat tasting salty, basically what affects is what
touches your tongue. So the כשר... kosher... so it's actually if you're
concerned about sodium intake you should use in general כשר kosher salt
rather than table salt. Never understood why table salt then it's easier
to make salt shakers that way. But basically, and I think the
same is true about... I always just use כשר kosher salt. I
think the same is true about about why it works for הכשר,
kashering, because the salt doesn't get in, it remains on the surface
more and it just brings out... does a better job of bringing
out the blood. And also, you know, you're going to get your
meat pretty salty in the process of הכשר, kashering, you'd rather not
get it too too salty. What about sea salt?
For הכשר? kashering?
Or I don't know. I mean, I think you get sea salt
that's big grains. Yeah, it's basically the size of the grains. Now
let's get actually interesting because this is the last thing we're going
to discuss now, because the salting discussion has moved between הכשר kashering
meat to transferring taste, so now we're going to end with a
discussion about הכשר kashering meat. So let's take a look.
אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, אינה בשר יוצא מידי דמו, eina basar yotzei
midei damo, blood does not come out of its... get out of
its blood, blood I said. Meat does not get out of all
of its blood. Remember before we talked about roasting and whether the
roasting, whether when you roast it all of the blood has come
out or not. And I believe who was it that had a
problem with it?
שמואל Shmuel there said when the juices ran off of his meat
he threw it to his dog. So presumably שמואל Shmuel felt that
the roasting did not get all the blood out, and when you
cut it, right, those juices are still blood. Now that you can
say by roasting again, because by roasting you don't have to get
out all of the blood, because if you... because whatever is out
is out and what's in is not going anywhere, and as long
as it's still in, it's not טרף. treif. But by salting you
have to get out all of the blood. Why? Because you're then
going to put it in a pot and cook it, and then
if there's any blood left, it's going to go out and come
back in. So by roasting maybe not all the blood came out,
that was a discussion yesterday, is the juices that run off after
roasting considered blood or not, can you eat them? There we had
we פסקן pasken that the blood did come out but and there's
no blood left, but it doesn't have to all come out by
roasting to make it כשר, kosher, but by salting it does. And
now we're going to talk about what circumstances can we assume all
the blood came out in the salting. So let's take a look.
אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, אינה בשר יוצא מידי דמו, eina basar yotzei
midei damo, the meat does not come out of all of its
blood, all the blood does not come out of the meat, אלא
אם כן מלחו יפה יפה, ela im ken molcho yafeh yafeh, you
have to salt it very well, ומדיחו יפה יפה, umadicho yafeh yafeh,
and rinse it very well. Okay, which is not so helpful. I
mean again it shows the importance of a mimetic tradition, right? I
mean, you know, I'm sure Joe, did you learn to salt meat
or was it only the women that learned how to salt the
meat?
I never learned how to salt meat. I know a lot of
meat comes salted already.
No, no, no, but I'm saying in Europe. How did people... did
the girls learn from their mothers? Did the men know how to
salt meat? No, but the women, girls learned from their mothers.
The men in Europe didn't go into the kitchen.
Okay.
Yeah, but they were butchers, so maybe they knew
something. Okay, anyway, alright, so it was a mimetic tradition. How are
you going to describe, you know, how are you going to describe
how much salt? You know, I mean I guess in theory you
could, a lot of this stuff is much easier learned in practice
than it is by trying to word it and describe it. But
that's what it says, it has to be salted well and rinsed
well. The reason you rinse it, by the way, is a similar
reason to why you have it in a vessel with holes or
a slanted board, because if you don't want it sitting in its
own blood, because eventually it will be reabsorbed. Meaning we've been discussing
why doesn't it reabsorb it even as the blood is coming out,
and whatever answers there are, there are. But you don't want it
sitting in the blood afterwards. So therefore, the same way you have
it on a slanted board and it runs off, also after you're
done, you have to rinse it to get off that remainder of
the salt and the blood.
איתמר itmar it was said, רב הונא אמר Rav Huna amar מולח
ומדיח. moleach umadiach.
You salt it and then you rinse it. ומתנייתא תנא umatniyata tana
and the Baraita we taught מדיח ומולח ומדיח. madiach umoleach umadiach.
You rinse it, you salt it, and you rinse it. ולא פליגי
velo pligi and they don't debate. הא דחלי בית טבחא ha de-chalei
beit tavcha
one is that it was already rinsed in the butcher's house, butcher's
store. הא דלא חלי בית טבחא ha delo chalei beit tavcha and
if it wasn't rinsed in the butcher's stores then you have to
rinse it when you get home. Now, we understand why you salt
it, we understand why you rinse it afterwards. Why do you rinse
it before? So there are about eight reasons given in the ראשונים
Rishonim why you rinse it before. Well, who cares that there's blood
on it? You're about to salt and get out the blood. The
basic פשט pshat of the answers are, it's something along those lines
that if you salt the blood on the surface, the salt will
take the blood out and keep it coming out. But the blood
on the surface, the salt actually might put it in rather than
pulling it out. That's one type of an answer. Or maybe another
answer, maybe if you don't get the meat soft from having rinsed
it, then the salt won't be as effective. Okay, so there's answers
along that line that it's either about making the salt effective by
getting the meat clean and soft, or it is preventing the blood
on the surface from getting back in, but there are about eight
different variations of that.
How hot was the water then?
Yeah, but you don't want to use too hot because then you're
going to put the blood in. Okay, anyway, by the way, I
don't know if people have ever looked, but if you take a
look, I believe on Morton's Kosher Salt on the side, it gives
you the rules for koshering. It's
really... go to your supermarket. I was going to bring it in,
I was going to bring it in, but I didn't have a
Morton's Kosher Salt, I had the other one, whatever, the Diamond or
whatever. Anyway, but take a look at the supermarket. I don't know
if they still do it, but just a year or two ago
I checked, and if you look at the side it says how
to kosher meat. It says slanted board, you rinse your meat, salt
it, wait 18 minutes I think they say, rinse it again. Take
a look at it. By the way, which is why it's called
kosher salt, because it's really koshering salt, koshering salt, not kosher salt.
That's... yeah.
If you have a salt problem, they say that even once before
you prepare meat, you should wash it again.
Aha, to get any residue salt off. Right. Yeah, you could just
roast all your meat, get it raw from the butcher and roast
it over an open fire, and then you wouldn't have to worry
about koshering it.
Or buy pre-koshered meat.
I was actually going to make special arrangements with the butcher.
Yeah, what were you saying before? Because in terms of conceptually, you're
saying there really is no conceptual difference why if you salt two
pieces of meat together, it wouldn't be a problem, whereas if...
the way it's explained is it's the qualities of blood, דם משרק
שריק. dam mishrak sharik. That's the way it's explained. Now, the way
you could test that and whether you would completely have the law
be just limited to the case of koshering is let's say you
had a case where, I don't know how you could create the
scenario, but if you had a case where you were salting non-kosher
meat and kosher meat together, and you were... and... טרף treif meat,
let's say חזיר chazir meat, you know, with a kosher meat,
and you somehow were not worried about the juices and it was
just the issue of the blood of the חזיר, chazir, then you
could test whether it's true because
then that's not blood needed in the koshering process, but it is
blood of non-kosher meat. But again, I don't know how you could
construct that scenario. The basic point is the rules work for koshering
and then for other things we assume that salting is a problem
and spewing out doesn't save you. Okay?
Alright.
What is the modern equivalent of משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu writing on
a rock when they went in?
Right. That's a good point exactly. I don't know why they started,
you know, why they did that. I mean, I guess, I mean
here I... you know, like I guess 50 years ago in America,
right, Morton's been around for a long time, people salted their own
meat. They didn't buy
pre-salted. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
okay. רב דימי מנהרדעא Rav Dimi Mi-Nehardea was going to bring it
in, but next tomorrow maybe. רב דימי מנהרדעא מלח ליה במילחא גלינתא.
Rav Dimi Mi-Nehardea malach lei be-milcha galinata. So he salted it, so
here you get maybe the idea of koshering salt, with this salt
of גלינתא, Galinata, which is I don't know some location,
does what's his
name Artscroll or... thick salt, there you go, koshering salt.
Okay, and it probably also means...
No, חלא chalei means vinegar. Okay, anyway,
okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on,
okay, ומנפיץ ליה, u-menafitz lei, and he sort of scattered it all
over the surface. So you, I'm sorry, רש"י Rashi said that, I'm
sorry, מלח גסה, melach gassa, רש"י Rashi said, מילחא גלינתא, milcha galinata,
thick sort of thick salt, and then he and he scattered it
all over the surface. So there you basically get the idea of
kosher salt.
Okay, and רש"י Rashi actually says that it doesn't just mean in
the process of surfacing, let's look at רש"י Rashi because this goes
to the question of why we don't use table salt. ומנפיץ ליה,
u-menafitz lei, it's about 15 lines from the top, רש"י Rashi says,
למילחא לאחר זמן, le-milcha le-achar zman,
so it actually doesn't mean just cover the surface of the meat
with salt, that maybe goes without saying, but to scatter it means
רש"י Rashi after it was sitting in the salt, meaning before rinsing
it off, right, you want to first shake off the excess salt.
So first you shake off the excess salt and then you rinse
it off.
And then he says, מפני שהדם נבלע בה, mipnei she-hadam nivla bah,
you don't want the salt to get reabsorbed into the meat. אבל
מלח דקה אין צריך לנפץ שהיא מתמסמס מאליה. Aval melach dakka ein
tzarich le-napeitz she-hi mitmamses me-aleha. So רש"י Rashi actually says that thin
salt would be better, thin salt you wouldn't have to shake off
because it would dissolve and wash away. But actually we know we
use דווקא davka the thick salt for the reason I said, it's
less sodium and it covers more surface and it doesn't get into
the meat, it stays on the top and doesn't make its way
into the meat. So the way it's described here by this רב
דימי Rav Dimi is pretty similar to what we do. So let's
read that again. מלח ליה במילחא גלינתא, malach lei be-milcha galinata, he
used thick salt, ומנפיץ ליה, u-menafitz lei, and he shook it off
afterwards. אמר רב משארשיא, Amar Rav Mesharshaya, said רב משארשיא, Rav Mesharshaya,
אין מחזיקין דם בפני מעיים. ein machazikin dam bifnei mei-ayim. You don't
have to worry about blood in the inner organs. The inner organs
don't have blood in them. Now what does that mean? So the
גמרא Gemara says,
תרגומא אכרכשא ומעיא והדרא דכנתא. Targuma a-karkasha u-mei-aya ve-hadra de-kanta.
So he said that this was referring to these are all different
parts of the stomach and the small intestine and the sort of
the digestive organs of the digestive tracts. I forgot to look it
up, does somebody there have what is large intestine? Large intestine, what
else? That's it?
Rectum, stomach, and large intestine.
Rectum, stomach, and large intestine. Thank you. Okay, so though now I
assume it's not true, I assume that every organ has blood vessels
in it, right? But the גמרא Gemara is saying that those for
whatever reason are not halachically considered דם. dam. Now I don't know,
are those is the blood in those vessels is there less blood
in those vessels than there are in other organs? Yeah, so I
don't know, but that's interesting that you do not have to worry
about salting those vessels. That is not those are not considered that's
not halachically considered דם. dam.
It's in the... stomach, you look for them?
Yeah, well it's the one that's called the... yeah, I don't know.
Okay, אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, אין מניחין בשר מליח אלא על גבי
כלי מנוקב. ein manichin basar maliach ela al gabi kli menukav. And
this is what we saw before, when you're salting it it has
to be either in a slanted board, which isn't said here, or
a vessel with holes in it. רב ששת... Rav Sheshet... thank you.
רב ששת מלח ליה
גרמא גרמא.
Rav Sheshet malach lei
garma garma.
So he did them each piece individually. He did not do multiple
pieces. We were sort of referring yesterday to the conclusion today, but
here we're first having an opinion that it's each piece individually. תרי
מאי טעמא לא? Trei mai taama lo? Why didn't he do two
pieces at the same time? משום דפריש מהאי ובלע האי. mishum de-parish
mei-hai u-vala hai. He was afraid that blood would run off of
one piece and get absorbed in the other. Right, we were yesterday
saying it's not an issue, but here רב ששת Rav Sheshet was
afraid of it. So the גמרא Gemara said, if that's true, חד
נמי פריש מהאי גיסא ובלע האי גיסא. chad nami parish mei-hai gissa
u-vala hai gissa. So even one piece of meat, let's be afraid
that blood will run off of the top and get absorbed into
the bottom. אלא לא שנא, Ella lo shna, we don't care, even
if it's running off of one piece and running on top of
the other, while they're being salted, that prevents the blood from getting
absorbed in the other piece. And as we said, long תוספות Tosafot
tries to figure out the exact principles, but basically you could salt
multiple pieces together. And תוספות Tosafot says even if you're let's say
you have them in rows and your bottom row was salted first
and your top row is salted last, so there's blood coming out
of the top row after the bottom row has finished, even so
we say that the blood will just slide off and he tries
to figure out what are the principles that allow us to say
that, but this גמרא Gemara makes it clear that as long as
you're salting multiple pieces you do not have to worry. אמר שמואל
משום רבי חייא, Amar Shmuel mishum Rabbi Chiya, one last statement, השובר
מפרקתה של בהמה קודם שתצא נפשה הרי זה מכביד את הבשר. ha-shover
mafrakta she-beheima kodem she-teitzei nafsha, harei ze machbid et ha-basar. מכביד את
הבשר וגוזל את הבריות ומבליע דם באיברים. machbid et habasar vegozel et
habriot umavlia dam baeivarim.
So if you wanted to get nice red juicy meat, what would
you do, especially if you have to salt it? So you could
just roast it lightly. That's always a solution. But here apparently what's
something that somebody was thinking about doing, which is why the גמרא
Gemara has to say you're not allowed to do it. What you
were going to do is, okay, you שחט shachat the animal and
before it died, right, while it still had a life force, you
broke its neck. And that actually caused it, you know, to the
blood not to fully spew out. I don't exactly get that, but
somehow that caused the blood not to spew out if you broke
its neck before after שחטינג shechting it. So שמואל Shmuel says don't
do that. Why not? Because it is מכביד את הבשר וגוזל את
הבריות. machbid et habasar vegozel et habriot.
Those are really one thing. Because the meat now will be heavier,
right? If you weigh the meat, there'll be more blood absorbed in
it. So if you sell somebody a pound of meat, it'll have
a higher blood content. So you are weighing down the meat and
stealing, robbing people. Why are you robbing people? Because if you're the
butcher and you're going to sell them a pound of meat, now
it's going to be less than a pound of meat, there's going
to be a higher blood content. And number two, I mean number
three, but it's really the first two are one, ומבליע דם באיברים.
umavlia dam baeivarim. The blood gets stuck in the meat and presumably
won't come out if you try to salt it. So you're going
to have a problem of טרף treif meat, too much blood.
It doesn't come out,
it's not a problem if you roast it. But if you salt
it and then you put it in your pot, right, when you
salt it, all the blood has to come out because then you're
going to put it in your pot and if there's any blood
left, it's going to go out and come back in. So when
you roast it, you don't have to get it all out, but
when you salt it, you do have to get it all out.
And we are saying here that if you did this trick to
get the blood to not go out when you שחט shachat and
to get absorbed into the meat, you're not going to be able
to כשר kasher the meat. The blood is going to get stuck
in the meat and the כשרing, kashering, even if you salt it,
the כשרing kashering won't be effective.
You mean like roasting on a spit? Is that what you mean
by roasting?
Yes, yes, roasting not in a pan, not pan roasting, roasting so
that the blood goes away, falls away, drips away. Right. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says איבעיא להו, Ibaia lehu, we raise a question.
היכי קאמר, Heichi ka'amar, what does he say? מכביד את הבשר וגוזל
את הבריות משום דמבליע את הדם באיברים, machbid et habasar vegozel et
habriot mishum demavlia et hadam baeivarim, that you are weighing down the
meat and robbing people because the blood is absorbed in the meat,
but actually it's not a halachic point about blood, it's just a
point about cheating people, that you're getting more blood in the meat,
but in theory you really could כשר kasher it. It's just you're
cheating people because now the meat weighs more. לדידיה שפיר דמי, ledidei
shapir dami, so if I wanted to do it for my own
use, I'm allowed to. Let's say I like blood in meat and
I want to do that, I'm allowed. We're not saying it can't
be כשרed, kashered, we're just saying that you're weighing down the meat.
או דילמא לדידיה נמי אסור, o dilma ledidei nami assur, or when
we say the blood is absorbed, do we mean it gets so
absorbed into the meat that כשרing kashering won't be effective? And the
גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku, we don't have an answer to that,
so don't do it. Okay, even for yourself. Now we can ברוך
השם Baruch Hashem put aside that very heavy stuff we did now
about a lot of classic כשרות kashrut stuff. First of all, מליחה,
melicha, salting, salting in terms of כשרing kashering meat, which nowadays nobody
worries about because the butcher does. Number one, salting in terms of
transferring taste, about נט בר נט, nat bar nat, cooking פרווה parve
stuff in מילכיג milchig or פליישיג fleishig vessels, חריף, charif, cutting onions,
a lot of very classic כשרות kashrut stuff. Now we move back
to the easier world of בשר בחלב, basar bechalav, of meat and
milk, which is going to return back now to in this משנה.
Mishnah. Yeah.
Just finish up very briefly.
Theoretically, raw meat that's been שחטed shachated but it's not, it's not,
so raw meat, there's no way theoretically.
Correct. Exactly. As long as the blood has not gone out, it's
כשר, kasher, which is also why roasting, as we saw yesterday, there
were some opinions that roasting didn't get all the blood out but
you could still eat the meat. Right.
How about what you still do today with the salt, the כשר,
kasher, the whole thing? How do they salt it?
I, how
do they salt it? I, as a whole piece? How is it?
Do they salt as a huge piece? Do they chop it up
first? I don't, I really don't know, I couldn't tell you. Now
the big question that comes up is that there's a, is that
there's a, a, what do you call it, a מנהג minhag from
the גאונים Geonim already not to, you can only salt the meat
within three days of it being שחטed shachated because we're afraid that
again the blood will get stuck and won't come out after salting.
And then the question is, you know, how do you deal with
it if you haven't, and can you rely on freezing the meat
or whatever, or you know, there's, the standard practice is to wash
the meat. If you wash the meat within every seventy-two hours, you
can extend the time. And you know, they used to tell stories
about like, I mean again, nowadays you know with the shipping speeds
or whatever, I think it's not, not a problem, but sometimes it
is, like when people import meat from Argentina or whatever, exactly like
in Israel. But you know, there's stories about like a rabbi getting
a call in the middle of the night at 2:00 AM from
like the train station, which is, you know, there's somebody here and
says that they need the rabbi of the town, you know, and
he schleps out and comes with his hose and he, you know,
rinses off the meat, you know, in order because you have to
rinse it every seventy-two hours till you salt it.
So, how would you salt the meat?
Well, now I think they do the salt, I don't know, I
assume... I mean Empire stuff obviously gets salted in the slaughterhouse. But
when you buy fresh meat from your butcher I think they salt
it at the at the butcher. Yes.
Someone told me and I haven't confirmed this that one of the
issues about the רבנות Rabbanut non-מהדרין Mehadrin הכשר hechsher is they allow
the meat to be frozen before it's salted.
Right, that is one of the questions about the Argentinean meat. Some,
you know, is about, that's one of the leniencies that they rely
on is that they freeze it and they then, and they say
that that extends the 72 hours. Well, there are opinions about that.
All right.
No opinion. All right. So now, so no comment.
Yes, there was a question on יום טוב Yom Tov about, I
think I missed the answer, cutting a radish. Is it the pressure
and the...
So that's a good question. It's, you need both the pressure and
the דבר חריף. davar charif. So for example, if you just, you
know,
if a radish, I'm trying to think of a scenario, if a
radish basically touches something without pressure, it wouldn't be a problem. Also,
radish is an onion. Cooking, cooking isn't the problem. It's the pressure
of the knife. Well, cooking I should say isn't the problem. The
process of cooking sweetens them, but the cooking itself does draw out
the taste. So cooking actually, yes, depending on when the cooking is
done, cooking in דבר חריף davar charif actually... In a cold pot
or... Yeah, it is the pressure of the knife. How exactly those
two mechanics work together I don't want to go into right now.
It could be that each one does half of the job. But
anyway, but yes, it is the cutting with, but yes, but cooking,
I should mention that. If you cook, if you
sauté onions in a פליישיג fleishig pot because onions are let's say
a דבר חריף, davar charif, then even if the pot is clean
and even if it hasn't been used in a week or whatever,
it's considered that it takes up the taste and the onions are
פליישיג. fleishig.
And they are פליישיג. fleishig. However, if you sautéed onions in a
פרווה pareve pot and then put those onions into a פליישיג fleishig
pot once it's been cooked, then it loses its חריף charif status.
Okay? And also if it's in a mixture with a lot of
other stuff, it loses, it's not considered חריף. charif. But if you
sauté just onions or just garlic and it turns out it was
a טרייף treif pot or a מילכיג milchig pot or a פליישיג
fleishig pot, you got problems because of דבר חריף.
davar charif. Even if you don't sauté them, just put them in
your pot?
Yeah, okay. Let's move on. All right? Okay. So, oh my gosh.
Okay. משנה. Mishna. המעלה את העוף עם הגבינה על השולחן אינו עובר
בלא תעשה. Hamaleh et ha'of im hagevinah al hashulchan eino over belo
ta'aseh. So if you remember way back when, we were talking about
not having cheese and meat at the same table at the same
time. Okay? So now we're saying if you did have them at
the same table at the same time, you haven't transgressed a biblical
prohibition. Well, that seems pretty obvious. The גמרא Gemara says האוכלו עובר
בלא תעשה. ha'ochlo over belo ta'aseh. It sounds like were you to
eat them together, it would be a biblical transgression. שמע מינה בשר
עוף בחלב דאורייתא. Shma mina basar of bechalav de'oraita. You see that
poultry is considered דאורייתא. de'oraita. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אימא
המעלה את העוף עם הגבינה על השולחן אינה באה לידי לא תעשה.
eima hamaleh et of im gevinah al hashulchan eina ba lidei lo
ta'aseh. No, it means that cheese and chicken at the table can
never even lead to a biblical prohibition because chicken is never biblical.
So again, we are now finally in the next משנה Mishna about
to see the actual opinions about which meats are included in the
Torah's prohibition of meat and milk. As you will see, there are
two tannaitic opinions, neither of which mention birds, okay, poultry. But the
גמרא Gemara is again doing what it did at the beginning of
the פרק, perek, trying to read into some of these opening משניות
mishnayot that speak about not having chicken and cheese at the table
at the same time a possible tannaitic opinion that chicken is included
in the biblical prohibition. But that is never said by a named
תנא. Tanna. That is a possibility that the גמרא Gemara attempts to
read into these earlier משניות, mishnayot, but it is very difficult to
understand why that should be true because as we're about to see
in the next משנה, Mishna, birds don't have milk, mother's milk. Okay?
So since it says mother's milk, it makes a lot of sense
that we're only talking about mammals. But nevertheless, here again the גמרא
Gemara is saying maybe there is this תנא Tanna and maybe it's
the תנא Tanna of the first few משניות mishnayot that actually says
that birds are biblical. We do not rule that way, but that's
an attempt that the גמרא Gemara tries to do. Let's take a
look. Yes, Michael.
Yeah, because we said before that העוף עולה עם הגבינה על השולחן
אינו נאכל, ha'of oleh im hagevinah al hashulchan eino ne'echal, בית שמאי,
Beit Shammai, בית הלל Beit Hillel אומרים לא עולה ולא נאכל. omrim
lo oleh velo ne'echal.
So
what
do
we need this משנה Mishna for?
To tell you that either, to tell you that we're talking about
rabbinic problems and we're not talking about... But the first משנה Mishna
we're just saying דאורייתא de'oraita and this is דרבנן? derabbanan? No, they're
saying דרבנן.
derabbanan. This is just saying be aware that this whole issue about
being on the table is only rabbinic, it's not biblical. Okay? And
that is important because of the next משנה, Mishna, because the next
משנה Mishna is exactly about to say that birds are not a
biblical issue. Although the גמרא Gemara tries to read in that maybe
it's implying that they are, the next משנה Mishna makes it clear.
So let's read... Actually, why was this all together? Like why do
we have... Because they're all the rabbinic issues. Let's read... The כחל
kachal and all that instead of putting this one back over there,
it like digresses a whole like ten different things and then we're
back to this again. That's a good question. Why it has כחל
kachal throughout? I don't know. Back to the next משנה. Mishna. בשר
בהמה טהורה בחלב בהמה טהורה אסור לבשל ואסור בהנאה. Basar behemah tehorah
bechalav behemah tehorah assur levashel ve'assur behana'ah. So kosher meat of a
kosher בהמה, behemah, which is like a mammal basically, you know, a
cow, a goat, a sheep, with the milk of such a kosher
animal, it's forbidden biblically to cook because here we're dealing now the...
Having them at the table is not a biblical prohibition. Let’s talk
now about biblical prohibitions. That's the structure of the משנה. Mishnah. So
if you have real meat of a mammal, kosher mammal like a
בהמה behemah together with the milk, then we're talking about a biblical
prohibition, you can't cook them together ואסור בהנאה ve’assur behana’ah and you
also can't even derive benefit let alone can you not eat from
it. Yes?
And what if you have the milk of a different type of
animal?
We’re going to talk about that. בשר בהמה טהורה בחלב בהמה טמאה
basar behemah tehorah bechol behemah tmeia let's say it is a the
milk of a non-kosher animal or בשר בהמה טמאה בחלב בהמה טהורה
basar behemah tmeia bechol behemah tehorah or it is the meat of
a non-kosher animal even though it's the milk of a kosher one,
מותר לבשל ומותר בהנאה. mutar levashal vemutar behana’ah. So you want to
cook meat and חזיר chazer meat with milk, or you want to
cook cow's meat with חזיר chazer milk, so you're allowed to cook
them together and you can derive benefit, obviously you can't eat it,
why can't you eat it? Because there's חזיר chazer there, but it's
not בשר בחלב basar bechalav and interestingly it's not even rabbinic בשר
בחלב. basar bechalav. Once you are dealing with חזיר chazer the rabbis
said what do we have to get involved, we're not going to
make this also forbidden as בשר בחלב, basar bechalav, so because they
didn't get involved, you're even allowed not only biblically but even rabbinically
to cook it together and to get benefit. By the way, not
as trivial as you would think, there's a whole question that comes
out with people that are learning to be chefs and how do
you do and how do you learn to do the dishes that
have meat and milk together, right, because even if you're not going
to eat from it, there's an איסור issur to cook them together.
So actually here's the solution, if you could I'm serious, if you
could get it to be use either חזיר chazer meat or use
חזיר chazer milk or something of that sort you actually would be
allowed to make to cook the dish, you wouldn't be allowed to
taste it. Now I want to be clear, this is only if
the species is not kosher. If you go to the store and
buy not shechted, you know, טרף treif meat, right, that is I
mean not shechted cow's meat, that is אסור בבישול assur bevishul ואסור
בהנאה. ve’assur behana’ah. They're talking about the non-kosher species, חזיר chazer meat
or חזיר chazer milk. Okay. Now how about chicken? Can you I
mean of course if you're doing these dishes you can't use a
chicken substitute, I don't even know if you could use a pig's
milk substitute, you certainly couldn't use a chicken substitute. But is chicken
אסור לבשל? assur levashal? So the רמב"ם Rambam learns from this משנה
Mishnah that anything that is not biblically prohibited, you can cook together
and you can get הנאה. hana'ah. Other ראשונים Rishonim disagree, they say
what are you talking about, this is a special case not because
it's not biblical because it's already טרף, treif, because it's טרף treif
the rabbis didn't get involved. But if it weren't טרף treif but
it were something like chicken and milk, right, then the rabbis would
get involved and they'd say don't cook it together, don't get benefit.
For God's sake, if you can't have them at the same table
then you also shouldn't be able to cook it together. But believe
it or not we rule like the רמב"ם Rambam and while we
rule that you cannot have chicken and cheese at the same table
we rule that you can cook chicken and milk together as long
as you're not going to eat it, as long as you're going
to give it to your dog or give it to your you
know or give it to your doorman you are allowed to cook
chicken and milk together. The reason is it points again to the
fact that although biblically cooking is the issue, by the time you
get to the actual practice, the emphasis has completely and the focus
has completely shifted from cooking to eating, so we will make a
lot of rabbinic restrictions around eating and don't even have them at
the same table even if it's just chicken and cheese, but we
won't make restrictions around cooking. It is a little bit bizarre and
ironic and I understand, but that is but that that is the
way the רמב"ם Rambam reads it and that's the way we rule.
But that's when we're talking about things that are not biblical like
chicken. Certainly things that are טרף, treif, no everyone rules like that,
right, certainly things that are that are not kosher species like pig,
it's מותר בבישול ומותר בהנאה. mutar bevishul vemutar behana’ah. One final comment
about this and then I'll take your question, which was oh
now
I forgot, מותר בבישול mutar bevishul ומותר בהנאה. vemutar behana’ah. Oh, yes,
by the way the איסור הנאה issur hana'ah is important and knowing
that it applies even to things that are already not kosher like
I mean like not shechted meat because of dog food. A lot
of dog food is meat and milk cooked together and if you
buy the dog food and give it to your dog you're getting
הנאה hana'ah from cooked meat and milk together. So that is where
the איסור הנאה issur hana'ah matters and you might say oh it's
not kosher meat it doesn't matter, but it's cow's meat even if
it wasn't shechted. There is some debate about that because remember our
whole סוגיא sugya about איסור חל על איסור. issur chal al issur.
So since נבילה neveilah is already forbidden, not shechted meat, does it
also become forbidden in הנאה hana'ah when you cook it together with
milk? You're not allowed to cook it together, the act of cooking
it is clearly forbidden, will it become forbidden in הנאה? hana'ah? That's
איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur that's somewhat debated. But
you gotta be careful if you have a dog not to buy
dog food or maybe cat food also that is meat and milk
cooked together unless it's חזיר chazer milk, unless right, unless exactly, I
don't think they have that.
What happens to the pot?
You
cook chicken and
milk,
the pot is טרף, treif, you have to כשר. kasher. Yes?
Okay,
let's keep it going. Alright, that was a little halachic digression. רבי
עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva Omer, that is the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma.
The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma notice mentions only בהמה. behemah. What is
not mentioned in the now by the way it doesn't mention. חיה
*chayah* like deer and it certainly doesn't mention birds. Now by the
way, the question was asked what if you have milk from a
different type of a בהמה beheima. *behemah*, cow's milk in- no, cow's
milk in in lamb or lamb's milk with cow. That clearly is
biblically forbidden because the only thing it allowed was of a non-kosher
species, but of a different one of the kosher species is clearly
included. Now, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר חיה ועוף אינם מן התורה
*Rabbi Akiva omer chayah ve'of einam min haTorah*. He clarifies, he's really
like clarifying the תנא קמא's *Tanna Kamma's* position. Birds and a חיה
*chayah*, wild animals like deer, are not in the biblical prohibition, שנאמר
לא תבשל גדי gedi בחלב אמו bechalav imo, ג' פעמים *shenemar lo
tevashel gedi bachalav imo gimel pe'amim*. It says three times don't cook.
פרט *Prat*, and the three times is גדי gedi *gedi*. We start
by an assumption that we mean generally meat and milk, which is
a funny assumption. We start by an assumption that it's more abstract
and general, and then the fact that it says גדי gedi *gedi*
three times is to limit the scope of how much meat. Only
meat that is very much like גדי gedi *gedi*. So it's limited
three times. פרט לחיה ולעוף ובהמה טמאה *Prat lechayah ule'of uvehemah teme'ah*.
One excludes- well, it's actually reverse, but the simplest thing to exclude
is birds, then חיה *chayah*, and then even things which are also
not like it, it's not a בהמה *behemah*, and then even things
that are בהמה *behemah* if it's a non-kosher בהמה *behemah*. רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGelili אומר *Rabbi Yosi HaGlili omer*, נאמר לא תאכלו
כל נבלה nevela. *ne'emar lo tochlu kol neveilah*. Here's how I know
it. It says don't eat all נבלה nevela, *neveilah*, non-shechted meat. נאמר
לא תבשל גדי gedi. בחלב אמו bechalav imo, *ne'emar lo tevashel gedi
bachalav imo*. And the end of the verse says, right, לא תאכלו
כל נבלה nevela, לגר אשר בשעריך תתננה ואכלה או מכור לנכרי כי
עם קדוש אתה לה' אלהיך לא תבשל גדי gedi, בחלב אמו bechalav
imo, *lo tochlu kol neveilah lager asher bish'arecha titnenah va'achalah o machor
lenochri ki am kadosh atah l'Adonai Elohecha lo tevashel gedi bachalav imo*.
So it starts by saying don't eat נבלה nevela, *neveilah* and ends
by saying don't eat a kid in its mother's milk. את שאסור
משום נבלה אסור לבשל בחלב *et she'asur mishum neveilah asur levashel bachalav*.
Things that are prohibited for נבלה *neveilah*, which is non-kosher meat is
not prohibited for נבלה *neveilah*, just for non-kosher meat. What's prohibited for
נבלה *neveilah*? Things like any בהמה *behemah*, any חיה *chayah*, and also
birds. So anything that's in the נבלה *neveilah* category, any kosher meat
which is in the- could be in the נבלה *neveilah* category is
forbidden to cook with milk. So maybe even birds. עוף שאסור משום
נבלה יכול יהא אסור לבשל בחלב *of she'asur mishum neveilah yachol yehei
asur levashel bachalav*. Maybe birds are included because they're forbidden for נבלה
*neveilah*. תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*, the verse teaches, בחלב אמו bechalav imo,
*bachalav imo*, the milk of its mother. יצא עוף שאין לו חלב
chelev, אם *yatza of she'ein lo chalav em*. A bird does not
have mother's milk. That's got to be the clearest ever- I mean,
how could you read a bird into this verse? There's no mother's
milk. But what he does include is חיה *chayah*. Yeah. So the
debate of רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* and רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* is
רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* would say that it's fundamentally starts with- with
including חיה *chayah*. Not fundamentally, it starts and ends with including חיה
*chayah* and therefore deer are included. Okay. Now let's take a look.
No, we have five minutes left, we gotta get a little further.
מנא הני מילי *Mena hanei milei*? Where do we get this from?
אמר רבי אלעזר אמר קרא *Amar Rabbi Elazar amar kra*. Where do
we get that גדי gedi, *gedi* does not mean just a kid
goat? וישלח יהודה את גדי העזים gedi ha-izim, *Vayishlach Yehudah et gedi
ha'izim*.
Judah sent the kid goat. But it has two words, kid, גדי
gedi *gedi*, and goat. Kid goat. כאן גדי gedi עזים *Kan gedi
izim*. So when it says explicitly kid goat, that means a goat.
הכל מקום שנאמר גדי gedi סתם אפילו פרה ורחלה במשמע *Hacol makom
shenemar gedi stam afilu parah urechelah bemashma*. It includes any- any animal
of a- any young of a- young. Right. Right. Well, okay, we're
going to talk about that in a minute. Okay, tomorrow. Anyway, even-
even a cow and a sheep, any young animal, any child of
a- of a בהמה *behemah*. ולילף מיניה *Veleilaf mineih*? Why don't we
say that no, the opposite? גדי gedi, עזים *Gedi izim*, that serves
as the paradigm, that says that גדי gedi *gedi* every time it
says kid means goat. הכתיב קרא אחרינא *Hachtiv kra achrina*, there's another
verse. By- by יוסף *Yosef*. ואת עורות גדיי העזים *Ve'et orot gedayei
ha'izim*. Right, and the- and the- oh, this
is by יעקב *Yakov*.
Of- of- of- of- of- of- of- of- of- of- of- of-
of- of- of- of- of- of- of- of- of- of- of- of-
of- of- of- of- of- of- of- of The one that says
that even two verses can serve as the paradigm, the בנין אב,
what can you say? Why not learn from both of those that
that's the rule, that גדי gedi, means goat? So no, תרי מיעוטי
כתיבי. trei miutei ketivi. It's even more limited. It says עזי העזים,
izi ha-izim, גדי gedi. העזים, the goat. So therefore since it says
the goat, it means here we're talking about goat, elsewhere גדי gedi?
means more general. So that's the first move of the גמרא Gemara
that גדי gedi does not just mean goat. Now the גמרא Gemara
does not say how do you know it means even the milk
of a different animal? Meaning yes, maybe any animal but only in
its mother's milk. How do you know a, how do you know
even the cow's milk with a goat? And how do you know
even a goat with goat's milk if it's not its mother's milk?
So that we haven't done. But the first step we've done is
to broaden גדי gedi does not just mean goat. Now we're going
to, now we're going to leave the תנאי Tannai discussion for a
while and introduce שמואל Shmuel and what שמואל Shmuel learns from the
word גדי. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, says שמואל, Shmuel, גדי, goat, לרבות
את החלב, lerabot et hachelev, so even not only the meat of
the goat, but even the fat of the goat. If you cook
the fat, the forbidden fat with milk, you transgress the prohibition of
cooking and it maybe is a double prohibition as well of fat
and בשר בחלב. basar bechalav. Fat is considered essentially a type of
meat. גדי לרבות את המתה, Gedi lerabot et hameta, and it says
goat to include even an animal that died, a נבלה. Again, even
though it's a kosher species, it's not a problem of איסור חל
על איסור issur chal al issur and both are forbidden. גדי לרבות
את השליל Gedi lerabot et hashallil to include the fetus, the aborted
fetus. גדי, so now we've said three גדי times he says גדי
is to be more inclusive, three times to be exclusive. How you
can read גדי both as a broadening and a narrowing is a
little unclear, the גמרא Gemara will get to it. גדי, so that
was the three that were broadening. Now here's three things that we
learn from גדי that are narrowing. להוציא את הדם, lehotzi et hadam,
the blood of an animal is not considered meat. So if you
cook blood with milk, it's not בשר בחלב. basar bechalav. גדי להוציא
את השליא Gedi lehotzi et hashilya to exclude the placenta or the
afterbirth, that's not considered meat. And גדי להוציא את הטמאה gedi lehotzi
et hatmeia to exclude a non-kosher animal, which in our משנה Mishna
רבי עקיבא and רבי יוסי הגלילי did that, but here he's learning
that from גדי, non-kosher animal.
Now that's three, that's six things we learned from גדי. Now we're
going to go on to the word בחלב אמו, imo, its mother's
milk. בחלב אמו, only its mother's milk, ולא בחלב זכר, velo bechalav
zachar, not milk that would come from a male cow, that if
somehow, and actually sometimes it can happen that men can lactate, so
that would not be included. בחלב אמו, mother's milk, ולא בחלב שחוטה,
velo bechalav shechuta, that was our whole big discussion about כחל, kachal,
not milk that was shechted, meaning if you shechted and there's still
milk in the udder, that is not biblically prohibited, that was the
whole כחל kachal discussion. בחלב אמו, it has to still be a
living mother and the milk has to come out when the mother
is alive. אמו, its mother, ולא בחלב טמאה, velo bechalav tmeia, it
has to be like the goat, so it cannot be a non-kosher
animal. So that's some new things we've learned out here that were
not in the משנה. Mishna. Let's just do a little bit more
in the גמרא Gemara about the goat. אהא תלתא גדי כתיבי aha
tlata gedi ketivi ושישה דרשינן, veshisha darshinan, how does שמואל Shmuel get
away with six drashas by גדי? He did גדי three times to
be inclusive, three times to be broadening, three times to be narrowing,
but it only says גדי three times. How can he get six?
No, the גמרא Gemara is going to say שמואל Shmuel really only
needed three of those drashas. Three extra were thrown in. קסבר שמואל
kasavar Shmuel איסור חל על איסור. issur chal al issur. שמואל Shmuel
basically holds that one איסור issur can take place on top of
another איסור. issur. So two of the things we included were really
only needed to be included because they were doubly אסורים. assurim. חלב,
chelev forbidden fat, and נבלה, not shechted meat. So the חידוש chiddush
there that you can have בשר בחלב basar bechalav is that even
though they're already forbidden, they can become forbidden again because of בשר
בחלב. basar bechalav. Well, he didn't really need a verse to tell
him that because he generally holds one איסור issur can take place
on top of another. דאיסור חלב ונבלה מחד קרא נפקא. de-issur chelev
ve-nevela mechada kra nafka. So that already you get from one verse,
meaning you don't even really need a verse from them. So חלב
chelev and assuming that it's taken for granted that חלב chelev is
considered meat, fat is considered meat, so the only חידוש chiddush there
was that you can have a double איסור, issur, and that's not
such a חידוש chiddush for שמואל. Shmuel. He can learn them, first
of all, he maybe doesn't need any verse, or it says here
he needs one verse, he gets them both with the same verse.
You certainly don't need two verses for that.
So that saves us one. דם נמי לאו גדי הוא. dam nami
lav gedi hu. Blood is not meat, that we knew without a
verse. We know that blood isn't considered meat. ושליא נמי פירשא בעלמא
הוא. veshilya nami pirsha be-alma hu. The placenta or the afterbirth, we
also know that's not meat, that's just like garbage, that's like, you
know, it's like the cow's urine or whatever, it's like something that
comes from the cow but certainly it's not meat. So three of
the verses we didn't use. We didn't need two verses for חלב
chelev and נבלה, they're all the same point, one איסור issur takes
place on top of another. We didn't need a verse for blood,
that's clearly not meat, and we didn't need a verse for שליא,
shilya, that's clearly not meat. So we only needed three verses. פשו
להו תרי.
pashu
lehu trei.
So you're left with two, meaning one to tell חלב ודם, chelev
vedam, I mean חלב ונבלה, chelev ve-nevela, חד לרבות את השליל, chad
lerabot et hashallil,
one to include the fetus. וחד למעוטי בהמה טמאה v'chad l'ma'utei beheima
tmei'ah and once to exclude a non-kosher בהמה. Okay, so we will
pick up with this tomorrow, but the point is that שמואל Shmuel
is broadening the things that we're saying and one of the new
things that he introduced is first of all what constitutes meat versus
not meat. חלב chelev, is meat, דם dam is not meat, placenta
is not meat, the embryo is meat. So what is the line
between meat and not meat? It's not just things that are part
of the animal.
And the other important question that he's introducing is איסור חל על
איסור issur chal al issur which we'll continue
tomorrow. In his dog food question, you have נבלה, you have חלב,
you cook it with milk, does it become doubly forbidden? And the
key question is will it also become forbidden in הנאה? hana'ah? Is
it forbidden to cook and is it forbidden הנאה? hana'ah? And we'll
pick up with that tomorrow. Tomorrow regular time and then at eight.
Yes. Oh, just the problem
of the dog food.
No, no, no, at eight at night tomorrow night. Tomorrow morning 7:30
and then tomorrow night at eight o'clock.
Tomorrow 7:30 in the
morning and then eight at night. Does that work?
I'll try to come to many of them.